DAN KLEIN: So the question is, how are
we going to be able to learn how to
act when we don't know what the actions
do or what rewards we'll get?
You might think we can just reduce
this to what we had before.
We can somehow still use value
iteration or expect a max.
And that's true.
What we're going to talk about
now is model-based learning.
In model-based learning, we reduce the
reinforcement learning problem to the
previous case of a known MDP.
So how do we do that?
Well, we try to build a model.
We try to figure out what the
transitions and rewards do and then
pretend that's the truth.
So here's how it works.
We're going to learn an approximate
model, based on our experiences.
Once we have that approximate model,
we will solve for the values, for
example, the optimal values
or policies, as if the
learn model were correct.
If we learned a model that's pretty
close, maybe the policy that our
dynamic programs produce
will be good ones.
So we'd like to learn an MDP that
we can use for value iteration.
How are we going to do that?
Well, we're going to, at times, find
ourselves in certain states, s, and
take certain actions, a.
Let's not worry for now about how
we decide what action to take.
Whenever we're in state s and we take
action a, various things happen.
So we end up with the various
s prime outcomes.
Over time, we count them up.
Some of them happen more and
some of them happen less.
Maybe one of them happens
90% of the time.
When we take those counts and normalize
them, meaning divide them by
their sum, we get probabilities.
For example, that frequent one
will have probability 0.9.
That is our estimate of the transition
function for that
state and action pair.
We do that for all state
and action pairs.
In addition, we discover that the
rewards associated with a state s and
action a and a state s prime whenever
we experience that transition.
So we're going to act for a while.
We're going to accumulate counts
of various things.
We're going to turn them
into probabilities.
And once that's all done, we have a
transition function t and a reward
function r.
They're probably not correct, but they
are structurally what we need to run
things like value iteration.
So we learn an MDP, and
then we solve it.
Now there are a lot of small points here
that are very important, like how
do you know how to act?
How do you know how many
counts you need?
How do you know how close
you're going to be?
We're not going to get very much
into those details now.
We'll come back to the idea of how to
learn a good model in the second half
of the course.
But for now, I just want to give
you a sketch of how this works.
Here's an example.
Let's say we're a grid world and
somebody gives us this policy pi.
I'm trying to, for now, sidestep the
issue of how we know how to act.l
we're going to follow this policy
for better or for worse.
And so what are we going to do?
We imagine our gamma is one, so there's
no discounting to make this
example simple.
And we have some experiences.
So for example, we might have the
following episodes of training.
So in these episodes, this is
four times playing the game.
For example, in the first episode, we
start at B. We go east into C. We go
east into D.
And then we take the exit action.
We transition to the terminal state
where the game is over.
And we receive our big
reward of plus 10.
In this particular case, you get a minus
1 living reward and a plus 10
good exit reward.
Episode 2 is the same.
Episode 3 starts in E, goes north into
C, and then east into the good exit.
Episode 4 is interesting because we
start in E, we go north into C. And
when we try to go east, we actually
end up in A because there's some
non-determinism.
And there, we're forced
to take the bad exit.
So this is what we've
got to work with.
In a model-based setting, what we
do with all of this experience--
which is not everything that could
happen, it's just what we personally
have seen--
what we do with this experience is
we try to figure out what the
transitions must be.
So we think, all right, I've been in
B. I've taken the action east, and
what's happened?
Well so far, 100% of the time, we've
ended up in C. So I'll write down to
the best of my knowledge right now,
let's just say that east from B has a
100% chance of resulting in C.
That's a transition function.
Similarly, east from C, we know that 3/4
of the time it actually went east
into D. But 1/4 of the time it went
north into A. Are those the right
probabilities?
Almost surely not.
But they're a reasonable starting point
for this simplistic version.
So what comes out?
We've learned now a model where
we have transitions.
This is probability one.
This is probability 0.75 and so on.
And we've learned reward functions.
Now, of course, we've only learned about
the things we've actually tried.
But let's set that aside until
later in this lecture.
What do we do with this learned model?
Well, now it's an MDP.
It's the wrong MDP.
Oh well.
But we still know how to solve it.
That's the idea of model-based
learning.
So let's think about exactly
what we just did and what
model-based learning is.
Let's imagine we had a much,
much simpler problem.
Let's imagine that my goal was to
compute the average age of people in
this class.
So I want to compute the expected
age, the weighted average.
How would I do that?
Well, we all know how to
compute expectations.
And so, for example, if I knew the
probability distribution over ages,
how many people are each age, then I
would have a straightforward way of
computing this weighted average.
And the way I do that is I'd say, well,
the expectation of this random
variable, A, I sum over all
of the possible ages.
And I weight each one
by its probability.
So it's just a weighted average
according to the
distribution over ages.
Easy.
In fact, this is all that's really
going on in these MDPs.
This is what happens at a chance node.
You take a weighted expectation
of values that are
one step in the future.
So here it is.
Here's the weighted expectation.
What's that mean?
That means I actually look up for each
value, oh, how many people are age 20?
Oh, that's 0.35.
And then I continue.
That's like solving an MDP.
You know the probability distribution.
And so you just compute the expectation
by summing everything.
Now what happens if we don't
know the distribution?
We're forced to rely on samples.
We could take a few samples.
We could take a lot of samples.
Obviously, the more samples, all
else equal, the more accurate
these things will be.
We're going to collect samples,
instead of the probability
distribution.
The model-based view is, all right, I
don't know the distribution over ages,
but I've got samples.
What do I do with the samples?
The model-based view is, I use
the samples to reconstruct an
approximation of what I didn't know.
So I say, all right, my empirical
distribution over ages is whatever the
samples say.
And now I've reduced it to the case
of the known distribution.
And I compute expectations the way I
always do, by summing over all of the
different ages and weighting each one
by their relative frequencies in the
distribution.
Why does this model-based thing work?
The reason it works is because,
eventually, you learn the right model.
So what else could we do?
We could stay in the same setting where
we don't know P of A. And we
could do what's called model-free
approaches here.
What we do in a model-free approach is
we average the samples directly.
So for example, this person's 20.
This person's 30.
I add up all of the samples and
give them equal weight.
And I take their, in this case,
unweighted average.
It's super important.
When I do this model-free stuff,
the averages are unweighted.
Why does that work?
That works because the ages that are
more frequent show up in more samples.
So they're already up-weighted by virtue
of the fact that they pop up
more often in the sample outcomes.
And because the samples are going to
appear with the right frequencies,
either approach is going
to do the same thing.
Now in this case, you look at this
and you think, it's pretty
much exactly the same.
It's just about how and
when you group things.
Nothing important is happening here.
And that's because there's no structure
to this example problem.
The algorithms are going to be very
different in the reinforcement
learning case, because there's
going to be structure.
Things are going to depend on the
other states around them.
But this is the high-level view of
model-based versus model-free.
In model-based, you learn the
probability distributions.
And then you reduce it to the
case of solving a known MDP.
In the model-free case, we just take our
samples as they come and average
them together.
And while the model-based way may seem
more comfortable at first, because it
reduces to a known case, we'll see that
the algorithms for the model-free
case are, in many cases, much simpler.